<?xml version="1.0"?>
<content collectionGUID="FB58F55C-9585-4C68-BAD6-2F593DC4614A">
  <lastEdited clientType="local-build-20130324" date="2013-03-24 21:04:11 +0000"/>
  <textBox id="generic-header-attribute" dynamic="no" visible="yes">
    <richText>windows debugging series</richText>
  </textBox>
  <textBox id="generic-title-attributes" dynamic="no" visible="yes">
    <richText>Introduction</richText>
  </textBox>
  <textBox id="generic-datefield-attributes" dynamic="no" visible="yes">
    <richText>6 de janeiro de 2013</richText>
  </textBox>
  <textBox id="generic-body-attributes" dynamic="no" visible="yes">
    <richText>For now and next few posts, I will put together some information related to Windows Debugging I have been studying. The idea is to share some details to help Windows app developers and support team to find bugs in app faster. Not only when the app was shipped but also during development cycle.&#xD;The topics to be discussed you can see below in the list of posts that will be updated every time time new one is published. So, you will be able to find all series references into one single place.&#xD;&#xD;Remember: this series is an introduction and you can find much more detailed information along the web. During the development of this series, I will show some interesting sites for you to improve you knowledge.&#xD;&#xD;Thank you!&#xD;&#xD;List of posts:&#xD;&lt;a href="perma://BLPageReference/62C2ACA0-45FF-4164-86EE-A3511F6EFE3D"&gt;Glossary&lt;/a&gt; - gives brief definition of keywords and expressions used along this series.&#xD;&lt;a href="perma://BLPageReference/A624AA72-70E3-43C0-99BE-E63D599E8485"&gt;What is Debug?&lt;/a&gt; - quick introduction of what I think debug is.&#xD;&lt;a href="perma://BLPageReference/1B5FFF65-769B-4CD8-9754-AE4691D6C2DC"&gt;Debugging Tools For Windows&lt;/a&gt; - introduces a set of tools useful for debugging provided by the Microsoft.&#xD;&lt;a href="perma://BLPageReference/3436BB31-741E-4422-A9AB-D1EDE8C3A0D4"&gt;Leak Diagnosis Tools&lt;/a&gt; - introduces two tools UMDH, part of the Debugging Tools For Windows and LeakDiag.&#xD;&lt;a href="perma://BLPageReference/26533099-01B2-418E-A089-7F85A61DC1B4"&gt;Application Verifier&lt;/a&gt; - introduces a powerful application for debugging.&#xD;&lt;a href="perma://BLPageReference/67BEBB94-BAA7-41FC-A700-13B4F8FBCE2F"&gt;Global Flags (GFlags)&lt;/a&gt; - introduces the gflags application used to setup application instrumentation.&#xD;&lt;a href="perma://BLPageReference/7E62AFE5-8899-42B7-A6F9-E97B1E11263B"&gt;ADPlus&lt;/a&gt; - introduces a tool to generate dump files from crash and hangs for postmortem debugging.&#xD;&lt;a href="perma://BLPageReference/9AB9878C-254E-484C-9DA7-551431324B22"&gt;WinDbg Part I&lt;/a&gt; - introduces the WinDbg tool and one of its most important command !analyze.&#xD;&lt;a href="perma://BLPageReference/CA876BE3-F8DF-4BC4-84C7-2F297084E790"&gt;Memory Corruption&lt;/a&gt; - describes what is a memory corruption and how to detect it.&#xD;&lt;a href="perma://BLPageReference/21234798-0B40-4094-8CC5-CFBBF91917F5"&gt;Stack Corruption&lt;/a&gt; - introduces what is stack data structure and its common issues.&#xD;&lt;a href="perma://BLPageReference/046D0673-9C73-43DA-98CF-20D44E638F40"&gt;Heap Corruption&lt;/a&gt; - introduces what is heap and its common issues.&#xD;&lt;a href="perma://BLPageReference/ADF98E8B-CD85-4B08-BEA0-3D954308A616"&gt;WinDbg Part II&lt;/a&gt; - this introduces more useful commands supported by the WinDbg tool that helps to identify an issue in dump file.&#xD;&#xD;</richText>
  </textBox>
</content>
